<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iniunctions exhibited the [blank] day of [blank] anno. M. D. XXXVIII.</title>
            <title>Injunctions. 1538</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1538</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00094</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108749</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844405</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844405</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9215</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00094)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9215)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 8:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iniunctions exhibited the [blank] day of [blank] anno. M. D. XXXVIII.</title>
                  <title>Injunctions. 1538</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
                  <author>Henry VIII, King of England, 1491-1547.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Thomas Berthelet Regius impressor excudebat. Cum privilegio,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1538?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Addressed to the Church of England.</note>
                  <note>An edition of "Iniunctions for the clerge" (STC 10086).</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Publication and distribution --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9215:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9215:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Iniunctions exhibited the <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> daye of ANNO. M.D.XXXVIII.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N THE NAME OF GOD AMEN.</hi> by the auctoritie and commiſſion of the moſt excellent Prince <hi>HENRY</hi> by the grace of god kynge of <hi>ENGLANDE</hi> and of <hi>FRAVNCE,</hi> defenſour of the fayth, lorde of Irelande, and in erthe ſupreme heed vnder Chriſte of the Churche of Englande. I Thomas lorde Crumwell, lorde Priuie ſeale, vicegerent to the kynges ſayd highnes, for all his iurisdiction eccleſiaſtical within this Realme, do for thaduauncement of the true honour of almygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty god, encreaſe of vertue, and diſcharge of the kynges maieſtie grue and exhibite (vnto you) <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> theſe iniunctions folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyng, to be kept, obſerued, and fulfilled vpon the peynes hereafter declared.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>FYRST THAT</hi> ye ſhal truely obſerue and kepe al and ſyngular the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hyghnes Iniunctions, gyuen vnto you heretofore in my name, by his gracis auctoritie, not only vpon the peynes therin expreſſed, but alſo in your defaulte nowe after this ſeconde monicion continued, vpon further puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be ſtraytely extended towardes you by the kynges highnes arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or his vicegerent aforeſayde.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> that ye ſhall prouyde on this ſyde the feaſte of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> nerte commynge one boke of the hole Bible, of the largeſt volume in engliſhe, and the ſame ſette vp in ſome conuenient place within the ſayd churche, that ye haue cure of, where as your paryſheoners may moſte commodiouſely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorte to the ſame, and rede it. The charges of whiche boke ſhall be ratably borne betwene you, the perſon and the pariſheoners aforeſaid, that is to ſay, the one halfe by you, and the other halfe by them.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM THAT</hi> ye ſhall dyſcourage no man priuely or apertly, from the readinge or hearynge of the ſayd byble, but ſhall expreſſely prouoke fiere and exhorte euery perſon to rede the ſame, as that whiche is the very truely worde of god, that euery chriſten perſon is bounde to enbrace beleue and folowe, if he loke to be ſaued, admoniſhynge them neuertheleſſe to auoyde al contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; altercation therin, and to vſe an honeſt ſobrietie in the inquiſition of the trewe ſenſe of the ſame, and to referre thexplication of obſcure places to men of higher iugement in ſcripture.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> that ye ſhal euery ſonday and holy day through the yere<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> openly and playnly recite to your pariſhoners twyes or thries together or oftner, it nede requyre, one particle or ſentence of the Pater noſter or Crede in englyſhe, to the intent they may lerne the ſame by harte: And ſo from day to day to giue them one lyke leſſon or ſentence of the ſame, tylle they haue lerned the hole Pater noſter and Crede in englyſhe by rote. And as they be taughte euerye ſentence of the ſame by rote, ye ſhall expound and declare the vnderſtanding of the ſame vnto them, exhortynge all parentes and houſeholders, to teache their chyldren and ſeruauntes the ſame, as they are bounde in conſcience to doo. And that done, ye ſhall declare vnto them the tenne Commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes one by one euery ſonday &amp; holy day, til they be likewiſe perfit in the ſame.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9215:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> that ye ſhall in confeſſions euery lente examyne euery perſon that commeth to confeſſion to you, whether they can recite tharticles of our faith, and the Pater noſter in englyſhe, and here them ſaye the ſame particularlye, wherin if they be not perfite, ye ſhall declare to the ſame, that euery chryſten perſonne ought to knowe the ſame before they ſhoulde receyue the bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the aulter, and monyſſhe theym to lerne the ſame more parfytely by the nexte yere folowynge: or elles lyke as they ought not to preſume to come to goddis bourde, without perfite knowlege of the ſame, and yf they do, it is to the great peryl of their ſowles, ſo ye ſhall declare vnto them, that ye loke for other Iniunctions from the kynges highnes by that tyme to ſtay and repell all ſuche from goddis bourde, as ſhall be founde ignorant in the premyſſes, wherof ye do thus admonyſſhe theym, to the intent they ſhoulde both eſchewe the peryl of their ſowles, and alſo the worldly rebuke, that they myght incurre hereafter by the ſame.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> that ye ſhall make or cauſe to be made in the ſayde churche, and euery other cure ye haue, one ſermon euerye quarter of a yere at the leaſte, wherin ye ſhalpurely and ſyncerely declare the very goſpel of Chriſt, and in the ſame exhorte your herers to the workes of charitie, mercy, and faith, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially preſcribed and commanded in ſcrypture. And not to repoſe their truſte or affiaunce in any other workes deuyſed by mens fantaſyes beſyde ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. As in wanderynge to pylgremages, offrynge of money, candels, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to fayned reliques or ymages, or kyſſing and lickyng the ſame, ſayinge ouer a number of beades not vnderſtanded ne mynded on, or in ſuche lyke ſuperſtition. For the doinge wherof ye not only haue no promyſe of reward in ſcripture, but contrary wiſe greate threttes and maledictions of god, as thynges tendynge to ydolatrie and ſuperſtition, whyche of all other offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces god almyghty dothe moſte deteſte and abhorre, for that the ſame dymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſheth moſte his honour and glorie.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> that ſuch feyned Images as ye know in any of your cures; to be ſo abuſed with pilgremages or offrynges of any thynge made thervnto, ye ſhal for auoyding of that moſt deteſtable offence of Idolatry, forthwith take downe &amp; deleye, and ſhal ſuffre from hensforth no candels tapres or images of ware to be ſet afore any image or picture, but only the lyght that comenly goeth a croſſe the churche by the roode lofte, the lyght afore the ſacrament of the aulter, and the lyght about the ſepulchre, which for the adornynge of the churche and diuyne ſeruice, ye ſhall ſuffer to remayne ſtyll: admonyſhynge youre paryſhioners, that Images ſerue for no other purpoſe, but as to be bokes of vnlerned men, that can no letters, wherby they myght be otherwiſe admonyſhed of the lyues and conuerſation of them, that the ſayde images do repreſent. Whiche ymages if they abuſe for any other intent, than for ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che remembrances, they commytte ydolatrie in the ſame, to the great daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their ſoules. And therfore the kynges highneſſe, graciouſely tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge the weale of his ſubiectis ſoules, hath in parte alredy, and more woll hereafter frauayle for thabolyſhynge of ſuche images, as myght be occaſion of ſo great an offence to god, and ſo greatte a daunger to the ſoules of his
<pb facs="tcp:9215:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>louynge ſubiectes.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that in all ſuche benefyces or cures as ye haue, whervpon ye be not your ſelfe reſydent, ye ſhall appoynt ſuche curates in your ſtede, as both can by their habilitie, and woll alſo promptly execute theſe iniunctions, and do their duetie otherwiſe, that ye are bounde to do in euery behalfe according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and may profyte theyr cure no leſſe with good example of lyuynge, than with declaration of the worde of god: or els their lacke and defautes ſhall be imputed vnto you, who ſhall ſtraytely aunſwere for the ſame, if they doo otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> that ye ſhall admit no man to preche within any your benefices or cures, but ſuch as ſhal appere vnto you to be ſufficietly licenſed thervnto by the kynges highnes, or his graces autorite, by thatch byſhop of Canterbury, or the byſhoppe of this dioceſe, and ſuche as ſhalbe ſo licenſed, ye ſhal glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receyue, to declare the worde of god without any reſiſtence or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> if ye haue heretofore declared to your pariſhioners any thyng, to thextolling or ſetting forth of pilgremages, to feyned reliques, or Images, or any ſuch ſuperſtition, ye ſhal now openly afore the ſame recante &amp; reproue the ſame, ſhewing them (as the truth is) that ye dyd the ſame vpon no grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of ſcripture, but as one being ledde and ſeduced by a comen error and abuſe, crept in to the church through the ſuffrance and auaryce of ſuche as felt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt by the ſame.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> if ye do, or ſhal knowe any man within your paryſhe or els where, that is a letter of the worde of god, to be redde in englyſhe, or ſincerely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, or of the execution of theſe iniunctions, or a fautour of the byſſhop of Romes pretenſed power, nowe by the lawes of this realme iuſtely reiected and extirped, ye ſhall detecte and preſent the ſame to the kynges hyghneſſe, or his honourable counſayle, or to his vycegerent aforeſayde, or to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyce of peace next adioynynge.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> that you, and euery perſon, vicare, or curate within this dioceſſe, ſhall for euery churche, kepe one boke or regiſtre, wherin ye ſhall wryte the daye and yere of euery weddynge, chriſtenynge, and buryenge made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your paryſhe for your tyme, And ſo euery man ſuccedynge you lykewyſe, and alſo there inſerte euery perſons name, that ſhalbe ſo weddid, chriſtened, or buryed. And for the ſaufe kepynge of the ſame boke, the paryſhe ſhall be bounde to prouide of theyr common charges one ſure coffer, with. ii. lockes and keyes, wherof the one to remayne with you, and the other with the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deynes of euery ſuche paryſhe, wherin the ſayd boke ſhall be layde vp, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che boke ye ſhall euery ſonday take forthe, and in the preſence of the ſayde wardeynes, or one of them, write and recorde in the ſame, all the weddyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, chriſteninges, and burienges made the hole weke before. And that done to laye vp the boke in the ſayde coffer, as afore. And for euery tyme that the ſame ſhall be omytted, the partie that ſhall be in the faulte therof, ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte to the ſayd churche. iii.s.iiii.d. to be employed on the reparation of the ſame churche.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> that ye ſhall ones euery quarter of a yere reade theſe, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:9215:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>former Iuiunctions, gyuen vnto you by auctoritie of the kynges high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes openly and deliberatly before all your paryſhioners, to the entent that both you may be the better admoniſhed of your duety, and your ſaid pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners the more incited to enſue the ſame for theyr parte.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> for as moche as by a lawe eſtablyſhed euery man is bounde to pay his tythes, no man ſhall by colour of duetie omitted by theyr curates, deteine theyr tithes, and ſo redubbe one wrong with another, or be his owne iudge, but ſhall trewely paye the ſame, as hathe ben accuſtomed, to theyr perſones and curates, without any reſtraynte or dimynution: And ſuche lacke or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulte, as they can iuſtely fynde in theyr perſons and curates, to cal for refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation therof at theyr ordynaries and other ſuperiours handes, who vpon complayute and due profe therof, ſhall reforme the ſame accordyngly.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>ITEM</hi> that no perſon ſhal from henſforth, alter or change the order and maner of any faſtyng day, that is commaunded and indicted by the churche, nor of prayer or diuine ſeruice, other wiſe than is ſpecified in the ſaid iniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, vntyll ſuche tyme as the ſame ſhall be ſo ordered and tranſpoſed by the kinges highnes auctoritie, The eues of ſuche ſaynctes, whoſe holydays be abrogated, only excepted, whiche ſhal be declared henſeforth to be no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge days. Ercepted alſo the commemoration of Thomas Bekket, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme archbiſhop of Canturburie, whiche ſhall be cleane omitted, and in the ſtede therof the feriall ſeruice vſed.</p>
            <p>¶ Item that the knollynge of the Auees, after ſeruyce and certain other ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, whiche hath ben brought in and begon by the pretence of the byſhop of Romes pardon, henſeforth be lefte and omitted, leſt the people do hereafter truſte to haue pardon for the ſaying of their Auees, betwene the ſayde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, as they haue done in tymes paſt.</p>
            <p>¶ Item where in tymes paſt men haue vſed in dyuers places in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions to ſynge, <hi>Ora pro nobis,</hi> to ſo many ſaynctes, that they had no tyme to ſynge the good ſuffrages folowynge, as <hi>Parce nobis domine,</hi> and <hi>Libera nos do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> it muſte be taughte and preached, that better it were to omytte <hi>Ora pro nobis,</hi> and to ſynge the other ſuffrages, beinge moſt neceſſary, and effectuall.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>AL VVHICHE</hi> and ſyngular Iniunctions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> miniſter vnto you, and to your ſucceſſours by the kynges hyghnes auctoritie, to me committed in this parte, whiche I charge and commaunde you by the ſame auctorytie to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and kepe, vpon peyne of depriuation, ſequeſtration of your fruites, or ſuche other cohercion, as to the kynges hyghneſſe, or his vicegerent for the tyme beynge, ſhall be ſene conuenient.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Berthelet Regius impreſſor excudebat. CVM PRIVILEGIO.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9215:3"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
